<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:base="https://dextersig.ca/blog" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Death, Taxes, &amp; Off-By-One Errors</title>
    <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog</link>
    <atom:link href="https://dextersig.ca/blog/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description></description>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>Does Canada&#39;s Tech Industry Have a Future?</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/canada-tech/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, there&#39;s been a large movement amongst Canadians to stop buying American products, and replace those products with Canadian-made alternatives. Discussing why that shift is happening is outside of the scope of this post, but watching this happen as a Canadian planning to enter the Computer Science industry is incredibly interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer software and hardware is one of the industries that Canada (and the rest of the world) relies on the United States for. Google, Microsoft, Amazon, Netflix, Apple, and all of the largest tech companies in the world are based in the United States. There are Canadian technology companies, but we mostly rely on the United States for our digital infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been researching differnet Canadian tech products lately, and I&#39;ve found some unique ideas that I&#39;d like to share! This is by &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; means a comprehensive list of Canadian tech though, just a few of the items that I&#39;ve personally tried and had a positive experience with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ploopy.co&quot;&gt;Ploopy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ploopy is a Canadian hardware manufacturer! Those are few and far between nowadays, so I wanted to highlight one of my personal favourites. Founded in 2019, their primary claim-to-fame is their trackball mice, but they also make a couple other items like regular mice, trackpads, and headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other shtick they have is open sourcing all of their work; documentation, build instructions, QMK/VIA firmware, even design files! They offer DIY kits for assembling the parts yourself, but it would be totally possible to create one completely from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They obviously also offer fully assembled products on their website alongside the DIY kits. This is how I ordered my &lt;a href=&quot;https://ploopy.co/product-category/trackball/adept/&quot;&gt;Ploopy Adept&lt;/a&gt; trackball, and daily usage has been a great experience so far! I&#39;ve been playing Ghostrunner 2, and it actually feels more responsive than my previous midrange Logitech mouse, which was a welcome surprise. The buttons are responsive and clicky, and an extra bonus is being able to fiddle with the ball during loading screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one small piece of criticism I have so far is that the type of sensors used to track the ball make a good amount of noise. This isn&#39;t a big deal for me, I actually like the noise, but it might put off others. I can&#39;t advocate for their quality, but there are unofficial mods to reduce the noise made by the sensors. That&#39;s the nature of open source projects: With the right skills anyone can modify things to fit their own needs. It&#39;s awesome to see a Canadian group following the same ideology that propelled companies like Framework to success, but with their own unique lineup of products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gem.cbc.ca/&quot;&gt;CBC Gem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian Broadcasting Corporation is a Crown Corporation that serves as Canada&#39;s public broadcaster. They&#39;re oldest continually existing broadcasting network in Canada, which means they have a large catalouge of Canadian-made content under their belt. They utilize this advantage to create some products that work as alternatives to American tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gem is the CBC&#39;s video streaming service. They carry a lot of Canadian made content, both new and old. It&#39;s a great experience to be able to comb through the catalouge of Canadian made content, the offerings they have feel much more meaningful than the tsunami of content on streaming services like Netflix or Hulu. I&#39;ve been working through a few different shows on there: Blackberry, Murdoch Mysteries, and Shitt&#39;s Creek are a few examples. I&#39;ve never had any issues with the streaming quality or bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of all is that there&#39;s a free ad-supported tier, and the premium tier is very affordable at $5.99 per month. For comparison sake, Netflix charges the same amount... to add an extra user to your account... &lt;strong&gt;with ads.&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix&#39;s ad-supported tier is $7.99 month, and the closest equivalent tier to CBC&#39;s premium tier is more than three times as expensive at $18.99 per month. Disney+, Amazon Prime, and other streaming services are even more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not a complete replacement for traditional streaming services (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crave.ca/en&quot;&gt;Crave&lt;/a&gt; is probably your best bet), CBC Gem is a quality, afforable, Canadian-oriented option. Even if you&#39;re not sure this is the right option for you, I highly reccomend at least trying out the ad-supported tier and seeing if it&#39;s worth upgrading to the premium tier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/canada-tech/(https:/mauril.ca/en/)&quot;&gt;CBC Mauril&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A less appreciated CBC app is their language app, Mauril! It uses the CBC&#39;s vast catalouge of shows and movies to teach French and English, the two official languages of Canada. It&#39;s a great alternative to apps like Duolingo, which have had lots of criticism levied at them for context-free teaching, a gamified system, and forcefully pushing AI onto their users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I haven&#39;t used it for very long, through a few days of usage I was able to recall a few words and phrases that I originally learned in my elementary school French classes. Your milage may very, especially for advanced users, but as a completely free service for Canadians there&#39;s nothing to complain about here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grapheneos.org/&quot;&gt;GrapheneOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m willing to bet that this will be the most surprising item on this list. This is a privacy-oriented mobile operating system that actually has their non-profit foundation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canadacompanyregistry.com/companies/grapheneos-foundation/&quot;&gt;incorporated in Canada&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who&#39;s been following my blog probably has seen this name before, as I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dextersig.ca/blog/posts/android-without-google-3-days/&quot;&gt;previously wrote in-depth about using it in a different blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Ironically, even I didn&#39;t know about their Canadian origins at the time! It simply stood out as the best option out of any of the aftermarket Android versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one catch in the context of this post, though: GrapheneOS only works on Google Pixel phones, an American company. If you already have a Pixel phone, I can 100% recommend it, the Sandboxed Google Play feature means you can ditch a vast majority of the spying that Google does without any loss in functionality. You can also look at buying a Pixel on the second-hand market to install GrapheneOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So, does Canada&#39;s Tech Industry Have a Future?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short answer is: I like to think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one hand, Canadian tech is currently facing a gargantuan &amp;quot;brain drain&amp;quot; problem. We live directly on top of the largest tech industry in the world, bar none. Canadian computer scientists looking to enter the industry can easily get a TN visa to work in the United States and recieve a comically better wage than working for a Canadian tech company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Canada has a very rich history of innovation in the technology space. ATI, now owned by AMD, used to be based out of Markham, Ontario. They&#39;ve been the primary competitor to Nvidia&#39;s monopoly on the GPU space since the bankruptcy of 3dfx in 2000. Blackberry pioneered the idea of mobile devices, and practically invented the modern smartphone. Even in recent times, we&#39;ve had success stories like Shopify, one of the largest e-commerce platforms in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a strong hunger for Canadian-based tech alternatives right now. It feels like every time I open the fridge, there&#39;s some forum post somewhere about how BlackBerry should get back into the consumer smartphone space, or how Canadian Tire has the infrastructure to rival Amazon. I&#39;ll be watching closely to see if any of these ideas come to fruition, and would happily make a follow-up article in a few years when these ideas had a chance to come to fruition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 13:00:00 CDT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/canada-tech/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub.Club Solved a Massive Problem with the Fediverse, and it Just Died</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/subclub-dies/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Decentralized Social Media is &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;. Imagine if someone on Facebook could follow people on &lt;s&gt;X, The Everything App&lt;/s&gt; the platform formerly known as Twitter, or message a friend on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An easy way of explaining decentralized social media is by referencing email as a base. Let&#39;s say I&#39;m using &lt;a href=&quot;https://proton.me&quot;&gt;Proton Mail&lt;/a&gt; and my friend uses Google Gmail. Despite the fact that we are using completely different apps from different companies, we&#39;re still able to connect. If someone has the proper know-how, they could even set up their own email server on their computer, and it would work with the apps offered by companies as a service. The &amp;quot;fediverse&amp;quot; works in a similar fashion to email but for social media, and ActivityPub is the underlying protocol. There are other protocols that achieve similar goals, but for the sake of this topic I&#39;m going to focus on ActivityPub. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/&quot;&gt;Being backed by the W3C&lt;/a&gt;, and having by far the most users compared to other protocols makes it the most relevant standard today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ActivityPub apps have all sorts of advantages over &amp;quot;traditional&amp;quot; social media. As an example, if a social media company starts &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enshittification&quot;&gt;enshittifying&lt;/a&gt; their platform, then you can easily migrate to a new platform, and still interact seamlessly with the content from the old one. Users can even keep their followers while transitioning between platforms!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ActivityPub also makes moderation a &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; easier. Moderation is done by individual servers hosting an &amp;quot;instance&amp;quot; of an ActivityPub app. This splits the heavy job of moderation into chunks manageable by just a few people; closer in scale to a Discord server than literally billions of posts every day. Additionally, there are features for instance administrators to block other instances. This means that instances that don&#39;t properly moderate their own content are a non-issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re interested in how this works further, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R3ptZ1W-FRA&quot;&gt;TechAltar&lt;/a&gt; has an excellent video that breaks everything down. Regardless of the inner workings, this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just some fad that is going to die out. &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinmastodon.org/&quot;&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.com/blog/2023/03/17/making-the-social-web-a-better-place-activitypub-for-wordpress-joins-the-automattic-family/&quot;&gt;WordPress Blogs&lt;/a&gt;, and even &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.fb.com/2024/03/21/networking-traffic/threads-has-entered-the-fediverse/&quot;&gt;Facebook&#39;s Threads&lt;/a&gt; are services with millions of users that have adopted the ActivityPub protocol and are able to communicate with each other smoothly. This creates a network of hundreds of millions of people that are able to communicate with each other, and that user count is growing fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, there are a lot of problems that need to be solved before the Fediverse can truly attain mainstream adoption. In my eyes, one of the biggest issues to be solved is creator monetization.   Currently, the main way that internet creators monetize their work is through advertisements (more on this later), or through walled-garden platforms like Patreon or KoFi. The advantages of using a decentralized network kinda disappear if creators have to redirect their fans to a centralized platform to keep themselves afloat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter Sub.Club, a specialized ActivityPub app that enabled monetization for creators. While the functionality was similar to Patreon or KoFi, what differentiated this service was that they took advantage of ActivityPub to specialize their service towards Fediverse creators. Accounts were linked directly to a creators&#39; already existing Fediverse account, and creators could post to their premium subscribers &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; from their main account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, by the time I found out about Sub.Club they had already shut down, just earlier this month. They used to have a website, but the URL is broken and I can&#39;t find any working archives on the Internet Archive. The only evidence I have that they even exist is &lt;a href=&quot;https://mastodon.social/@subclub&quot;&gt;their (abandoned) Mastodon profile&lt;/a&gt;, and some articles written for The Verge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2024/12/16/24322574/sub-club-mastodon-mammoth-fediverse-shutting-down&quot;&gt;Based on those Verge articles&lt;/a&gt;, it looks like Sub.Club shut down due to lack of funding. Considering how small the demographic is for a service like Sub.Club, and how they only launched in August last year, it makes sense why a shutdown had to happen. I&#39;m still upset about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federated social media &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; a method of monetization, especially in regards to the creators. Advertisements aren&#39;t an answer, at least not as they exist right now. If a service or creators implement advertisements to make ends meet, users will just move to another ActivityPub app and continue to enjoy not having ads. Without services like Sub.Club, the largest creators, the ones with fans that will make the largest impact to the adoption of ActivityPub, won&#39;t be able to properly migrate to federated social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where does this leave things? Personally, I love the idea behind the Fediverse. &lt;a href=&quot;https://mstdn.ca/@threedollarchickenparm&quot;&gt;I recently made a Mastodon account for byte-sized intrusive thoughts&lt;/a&gt;. I also plan to migrate the larger intrusive thoughts on this site to an ActivityPub-enabled blogging service. However, I do both of these for fun, and don&#39;t expect to make a living off of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ActivityPub&#39;s interoperability is the future of social media. Some companies like Facebook have already noticed the many advantages, but creators need a method of monetizing the content that they make. With those large creators and their audiences, the Fediverse would grow exponentially faster, and social media would be that much better for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you have any thoughts or opinions you&#39;d like to discuss, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mstdn.ca/@threedollarchickenparm&quot;&gt;I&#39;d love to hear from you over on the Fediverse&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 12:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/subclub-dies/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canada&#39;s Exciting New Right to Repair Laws Have a Large Problem</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/canadas-massive-right-to-repair-win/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Canadians and Right to Repair activists scored a win! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parl.ca/legisinfo/en/bill/44-1/c-244?view=progress&quot;&gt;Bill C-244&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parl.ca/legisinfo/en/bill/44-1/c-294?view=details&quot;&gt;Bill C-294&lt;/a&gt; are the first federal bills in support of the Right to Repair movement to be passed, &lt;em&gt;in any country&lt;/em&gt;. Despite one inescapable problem with the bill, I still consider it an overall win for repair groups across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s start by recapping the story so far. Simply put, the Right to Repair movement aims to give individuals the ability to modify and repair their technology products as they please. A common misunderstanding is that Right to Repair would &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; people to repair their own technology, which isn&#39;t the case. We just want the ability to repair technology without any involvement from the manufacturer; it&#39;s totally okay if Apple, John Deere, or any company &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; offers repair services for their own hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I used the word &amp;quot;we&amp;quot; when talking about this movement. Full disclosure inbound; I am a &lt;strong&gt;strong&lt;/strong&gt; proponent of Right to Repair, and I also happens to live in Canada! Putting my personal interest in modifying and repairing technology aside, the ability to work on hardware without permission of the manufacturer creates less environmental waste, the individual components are cheaper than buying an entire replacement device, and expanding the repair industry creates jobs to serve people who don&#39;t know how to repair their own technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pluralistic.net/2024/11/15/radical-extremists/&quot;&gt;Cory Doctorow covers these aspects of repair in much more depth&lt;/a&gt; during his own post about the new Canadian bills. I highly recommend reading the post for yourself, to grasp a more in-depth understanding of the benefits seen in Right to Repair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the largest challenges around Right to Repair is heavy-handed usage of Technological Protection Measures, referred to as TPMs for short. Ever wonder where the joke about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2024/10/25/24279371/mcdonalds-ice-cream-machines-right-to-repair-copyright&quot;&gt;McDonald&#39;s ice cream machines always being broken&lt;/a&gt; came from? It&#39;s because (up until now!), the manufacturer of these machines, Taylor, added TPMs that prevented third-party repair, so that their repair technicians were the only ones who could fix the machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking past a TPM also &lt;s&gt;qualifies&lt;/s&gt; qualified as a Copyright violation. Originally, TPMs were developed as an anti-piracy measure. However, awhile after copyright law was updated to outright ban the breaking of TPMs, companies started using the technology to restrict access to repairing devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada&#39;s new legislation is pretty straightforward: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parl.ca/legisinfo/en/bill/44-1/c-244?view=progress&quot;&gt;Bill C-244&lt;/a&gt; is an exception to the Copyright Act that allows for repairing devices. If that weren&#39;t enough, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parl.ca/legisinfo/en/bill/44-1/c-294?view=details&quot;&gt;Bill C-294&lt;/a&gt; specifically amends the Copyright Act to allow for interoperability. This would bypass the frequent anti-repair practice of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ifixit.com/News/69320/how-parts-pairing-kills-independent-repair&quot;&gt;parts pairing&lt;/a&gt;, where companies tie the model number of two components to each other, in order to prevent third-party replacements from being installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it&#39;s great to see these bills passed, there&#39;s a large problem; while technicians might have permission to bypass a TPM...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theregister.com/2024/11/12/canada_right_to_repair/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;getting access&lt;/em&gt; to the tools required is still illegal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a massive asterisk on the bill that really dampens the entire win. After all, if I want to repair something with a complicated TPM, it becomes impractical to spend a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; of time developing the skills and knowledge to reverse-engineer and implement the crack myself, without discussing with anyone else in any form. The laws go from a massive win for Right to Repair, to a avenue for politicians to virtue signal about Right to Repair. This hurdle being kept in place after new legislation is &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; enough to not celebrate over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Almost&lt;/em&gt;. I like to take a more &amp;quot;Glass Half-Full&amp;quot; approach to technology discussions where I can, and there&#39;s still a lot to be excited about regarding the new bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, this isn&#39;t the first bill to be passed with similar amendments to equivalents of our countries&#39; Copyright Act, but it is the first to be passed &lt;em&gt;on a federal level&lt;/em&gt;. That sets a precedent for other countries to do the same. It would be great to see this kind of amendment to Copyright law become a standard across developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That universality would be great because there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; some simple TPMs that are possible to bypass individually. Primarily, this would effect simple password locks, especially on slightly older devices where passwords might be small enough that modern technology can crack a password relatively quickly and simply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the new bills are a first domino, tipped over and leading to stronger repair legislation. There are lots of ways to go about it. Further amendments to the Copyright Act that allow for the distribution of repair tools, or a bill that prevents companies from implementing TPMs that restrict hardware repair would be perfect. It would be even more exciting to see my home country at the forefront of that groundbreaking legislation. If you feel the same, please consider supporting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canrepair.ca/&quot;&gt;CanRepair&lt;/a&gt;, the amazing Right to Repair group that got the new bills passed in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 12:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/canadas-massive-right-to-repair-win/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Linux: Is It Difficult?</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/switching-to-linux-difficulty/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short answer: Yes. But also, no? It&#39;s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jumping into Linux with no research, no understanding, and no backup plan if it doesn&#39;t work out can be... frustrating. There are horror stories online about folks who dive head-first into Linux because they&#39;re tired of Microsoft&#39;s shenanigans. Then, they get overwhelmed with how different it can be from Windows. Then, they move off Linux because of the problems they face. Truthfully, I also felt upset with Linux when I first started using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do you do if you&#39;re interested in getting away from Microsoft&#39;s privacy disaster? The most important thing to do when learning the Linux ecosystem is to &lt;em&gt;move slow&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started out by installing Linux Mint alongside my copy of Windows 10 on my SSD, commonly referred to as dual booting. I only used it sometimes, or until I ran into a problem that I wouldn&#39;t be able to fix with my (extremely limited) knowledge. It worked okay most of the time, but there were a few small annoyances that I didn&#39;t understand how to fix, so I spent most of my time on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One morning, Windows randomly deleted my wifi drivers that I needed to register for university courses. Thankfully, my installation of Linux Mint connected to the internet completely fine. I was totally okay to register for courses because I had Linux installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I started using Mint more and more often. I eventually learned how to eliminate or reduce those annoyances from earlier. About a year and a half after installing Linux for the first time, I don&#39;t even have Windows installed on any of my systems. I&#39;m currently using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.debian.org/&quot;&gt;Debian 12&lt;/a&gt; full time, and I rarely run into issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing you should do; &lt;em&gt;backups, backups, backups&lt;/em&gt;! Make sure &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; valuable data is backed up somewhere that won&#39;t be affected by installing a new operating system. Linux won&#39;t delete your Windows installation if you don&#39;t select that (more on this later), but there&#39;s always the possibility of an accidental mistake. The goal is to be able to wipe the computer completely and start with a fresh installation of Windows without permanently losing any important photos, videos, or other data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picking a &amp;quot;distribution&amp;quot; of Linux is probably the most difficult and intimidating part of the process. There are hundreds of different variants out there, and it&#39;s not immediately clear what the differences are. A good choice for a first time user should be recognized by the wider Linux community as an option that&#39;s friendly for beginners. For the love of everything computing, do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; start with &lt;a href=&quot;https://archlinux.org/&quot;&gt;Arch Linux&lt;/a&gt;. It should have a large community of users behind it, so that troubleshooting steps are easy to find. Many people&#39;s first recommendation is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linuxmint.com/&quot;&gt;Linux Mint&lt;/a&gt;, which was also my first distro. &lt;a href=&quot;https://zorin.com/os/&quot;&gt;ZorinOS&lt;/a&gt; is also a great option, and might feel more familiar for people switching from an Apple device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&#39;ve chosen a distro, install it &lt;em&gt;alongside&lt;/em&gt; your other operating system. Dual boot on the same SSD as your gaming rig, overwrite that ten year old laptop gathering dust in your closet, or even try things out in a virtual machine first. &lt;strong&gt;Please don&#39;t purge Windows from your life right at the start!&lt;/strong&gt; Even if you only use Linux once a month, it still gets you a little bit more comfortable each time. There are a lot of Windows programs that are difficult or even impossible to get working, so you need to make sure that you have everything you need on Linux before a complete switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transitioning to Linux can be difficult without tempered expectations. I wouldn&#39;t call it more difficult to use than Windows, but it can definitely feel that way because it&#39;s different. Make sure to backup any important data to another device, pick a good beginner distro, and please don&#39;t fully erase Windows right at the start. Missing any of these steps can lead to massive frustrations. Following the steps makes the process of getting away from Windows or Apple not just less stressful, but even enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 13:00:00 CDT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/switching-to-linux-difficulty/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Own Your PC Games: A Comprehensive Guide to Avoiding DRM</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/how-to-own-your-pc-games/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The PC Gaming industry is absolutely crazy right now. Controversies surrounding Digital Rights Management, usually shorthanded to DRM, feel as old as PC gaming itself, but the last couple weeks have seen a particularly strong anger directed at the practice. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/articles/delisting-the-crew-makes-sense-preventing-it-from-ever-being-played-again-does-not&quot;&gt;Ubisoft is under fire for shutting down The Crew&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcgamer.com/games/third-person-shooter/with-over-84-thousand-negative-helldivers-2-steam-reviews-in-two-days-developer-arrowhead-seems-to-be-grappling-with-sony-over-its-controversial-psn-sign-in-requirement/&quot;&gt;Helldivers 2&#39;s rating on Steam has nose-dived because of a (now-reversed) PlayStation Network account requirement&lt;/a&gt;. With tensions between publishers and gamers growing more and more intense, it begs the question: What can we do as consumers to fully own our games?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this topic ties into a larger issue surrounding media ownership in the digital age. Many individuals, including myself, are upset with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enshittification&quot;&gt;enshittification&lt;/a&gt; of subscription services for movies, music, or even video games. Monthly prices seem to be climbing higher and higher, features and functionality are getting worse, and the companies that run these services have the power to remove or add content at their own discretion. In contrast, Blurays/DVDs and CDs (especially on the second hand market!) have never been as cheap as they are now, and purchasing a physical disk means that the customer has access to that content until the disk is lost or stops working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video games can be one of the most difficult forms of media to own. Network-based DRM has existed since the mid-2000&#39;s, and we&#39;ve already started to see the ramifications of this via games that can&#39;t be legally accessed anymore, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QZYy9KzFT2w&quot;&gt;which this YouTube video highlights excellently.&lt;/a&gt; Nowadays, physical releases of video games are practically nonexistent. Instead, most games can be bought on digital storefronts like Steam or Epic Games Store. These platforms provide extensive DRM options to their developers, so extensive that &amp;quot;buying a game&amp;quot; on these platforms is more like buying a license to play the game. These publishers can, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/articles/delisting-the-crew-makes-sense-preventing-it-from-ever-being-played-again-does-not&quot;&gt;and have&lt;/a&gt;, exercised their ability to remove this license, taking away the game that was paid for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have approached discussion of this subject from all sorts of different perspectives. One perspective that I haven&#39;t seen a lot of yet is what to do about it. Most of the discussion online revolves around the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stopkillinggames.com/&quot;&gt;Stop Killing Games&lt;/a&gt; initiative. I want to clarify right now that this is an excellent initiative. I have nothing but praise and respect for those working on it behind the scenes, and anyone reading these words right now should take the time out of their day to click that link and take action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I must also underscore that what Stop Killing Games aims to do will likely take a long time, years if not decades. What if someone wants to own their games &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;? Well, that&#39;s where this article fits in! Where can you, the reader, actually purchase a game and not just a license to play one? Hopefully by the end of this article, answering this question should be relatively straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, it&#39;s important to note that this guide is exclusively focused on &lt;em&gt;legal&lt;/em&gt; methods of obtaining DRM-Free games. I&#39;m a subscriber to the philosophy of voting with my wallet and my time. Instead of pirating a cracked version of a game with DRM, forego that game outright and play something that&#39;s legally obtainable. Piracy is relevant to the topic of DRM-Free gaming, making it important to acknowledge, but it&#39;s also complex, legally or ethically grey in many cases, and outside the scope of this guide. By extension, console games are also disqualified from conversation here unless the game has been officially released on PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GOG&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gog.com/&quot;&gt;GOG, short for Good Old Games&lt;/a&gt;, is the gold standard for DRM-Free gaming. While a launcher is provided for things like achievements and playtime tracking, any game on the platform also has installation files downloadable from a web browser. These files can be ran after downloading to install the game on a computer, no launcher or internet connection required! Here are some notable publishers and franchises that can be found on the platform:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bethesda:&lt;/strong&gt; Many of Bethesda&#39;s largest franchises are available on GOG. The Elder Scrolls, Fallout, Doom, Dishonoured, Wolfenstein, and others are all readily available and regularly discounted. The one catch is that some more recent games aren&#39;t available, games like Doom 2016/Eternal or Fallout 76 have not been released.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PlayStation:&lt;/strong&gt; Ironically, even while under fire for the Helldivers 2 controversy, Sony offers the Uncharted Legacy Collection, God of War 2018, and Horizon Zero Dawn for purchase on GOG. These are all excellent modern games that, despite releasing as far back as 7 years ago, still look great!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CD Project Red:&lt;/strong&gt; Fun Fact; GOG is actually a subsidiary of CD Project Red! Most, if not all of the studio&#39;s games are available on the platform, including The Witcher 3 and Cyberpunk 2077.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Larian Studios:&lt;/strong&gt; Most recently recognized for Baldurs Gate 3, Larian also offers their entire portfolio on GOG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is extremely far from a comprehensive list, just the developers that were most notable to me personally. GOG is &lt;em&gt;the place&lt;/em&gt; to go for buying games from recognizable franchises, without any DRM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;itch.io&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itch.io/&quot;&gt;itch.io&lt;/a&gt; is also an excellent option for buying DRM-free games, alongside GOG. this platform is mainly oriented towards indie developers, making a bit of a wild west in the context of game storefronts. What&#39;s most important to know is that &lt;strong&gt;not every game is free of DRM.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, lots of developers offer the game files as a download, but some only offer a key to a Steam installation, which could have DRM associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes itch.io such a great store alongside GOG is that they host a lot of the smaller developers that haven&#39;t published their stuff on any other DRMless platforms. Games like Celeste, Towerfall Ascension, Baba is You, A Dance of Fire and Ice, Skatebird, and other big names are all easy to download, backup, and fully own. It&#39;s also a great spot for discovering indie games or developers of you ever get sick of the mainstream (but still very good!) selection on GOG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Steam and other Storefronts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might seem contradictory at first. After all, haven&#39;t I just spent most of this article offering alternatives to storefronts like Steam, and even emphasizing how access to games can be blocked on these platforms later down the line?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bad news is that Steam is the absolute largest digital games storefront on the PC, so most developers will choose to publish there first. The good news is that DRM is not a requirement, so lots of developers publish games on these platforms that don&#39;t require the platform&#39;s tools to run. Here are a few examples of games on Steam that can be played independent of the platform:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hades:&lt;/strong&gt; A great example of a modern game on Steam with absolutely zero DRM. Supergiant have published five games (one in early access) at time of writing, and the Hades games have been their most successful so far. At time of writing, Hades and Hades 2 are nowhere to be seen on GOG (despite the rest of their portfolio being available here), itch.io, or any PC platform besides Steam and Epic Games. The good news is that Hades is completely DRM-free on Steam and Epic Games, so downloading the game files from Steam and copying them from the default directory would work just as well as a download off of itch.io. I did it myself, and it worked great! I now have a backup alongside my GOG and itch.io libraries. This made me really happy, as Hades is one of my favourite games ever and I would hate to lose access to it later down the line. I couldn&#39;t get Hades 2 to work outside of Steam, but Supergiant has yet to release a game with DRM, so hopefully this issue changes once the 1.0 version of the game releases because it&#39;s also a masterpiece so far.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spiritfarer:&lt;/strong&gt; Spiritfarer is an amazing game, and is available for download on GOG! You might be confused as to why I&#39;m discussing it here, then. Well, I originally purchased the game on Steam before discovering that GOG existed, so I paid for a version with DRM. Thankfully, the DRM is trivial to bypass. the only thing stopping it from loading is needing to create a &amp;quot;steamapp_id.txt&amp;quot; file in the root folder of the game, and adding the public ID of the game to the file (For Spiritfarer, it&#39;s 972660). Finding the ID of the game is as simple as looking up the title on (SteamDB)[https://steamdb.info/]. This is also a great example of how, if achievements and other launcher features aren&#39;t of importance, double dipping on games for a DRM-Free version is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a requirement in some cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Factorio:&lt;/strong&gt; I personally haven&#39;t played Factorio, but it&#39;s a great example of how, even when DRM is difficult to bypass on one version of a game, obtaining a DRM free copy is still doable. The developer offers a steam login on their homepage, and using that login with an account that has bought the game will give players access to a downloadable copy, no DRM included.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steam should be a last resort for gamers looking to own their games. GOG has a strict policy against DRM, while itch.io&#39;s style of publishing games means that it&#39;s very easy to determine whether the game is DRM free or not. Steam has no such safety net, and games without DRM can be updated later down the line to include it. It&#39;s still an option to check for the occasional developer that hasn&#39;t published anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;After buying the games&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This really depends on a lot of things, from the choice of operating system to the personality of the customer. Want to use GOG exactly like Steam? Totally doable! Paranoid about the apocalypse and want to create three dozen backups of the installers? Cool, sounds good! I&#39;ll discuss my experience with owning the games and the installation files, but will also discuss different routes as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, a way to launch the games is crucial in order to play them. The installers from GOG and game files from itch.io can be used and played without a traditional game launcher, but there are also lots of options for playtime tracking, achievements, and more if that&#39;s of interest. Linux has both the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heroicgameslauncher.com/&quot;&gt;Heroic Games Launcher&lt;/a&gt; and my launcher of choice, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lutris.net/&quot;&gt;Lutris&lt;/a&gt;. On Windows, GOG and itch.io both offer official launchers for games purchased on their platforms. All of these options work great, so consider your wants and needs, research these options (or others I missed!) and decide from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backups of games also are a good idea, especially when buying from a platform like Steam where DRM can be added in an update. Digital backups are an entire can of worms in itself that I won&#39;t go into detail about much here (although plan to in the future!). For now, know that Lutris supports installing games through GOG&#39;s installer files rather than downloading the game over again, a very strong selling point for those who plan to backup those installation files anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, doing none of this and just using these platforms exactly like Steam is an option. That&#39;s the beauty of owning games this way: customers get the &lt;strong&gt;options&lt;/strong&gt; to do what they want with their games. When research started for this article, the hypothesis was that it would be a big sacrifice to only buy games this way, but in retrospect there isn&#39;t that much compromise here! Most big names in the industry have at least a few games available through GOG, itch.io is literally built for indie developers, and even some titles I had already bought on Steam can be backed up and played how I&#39;d like to. I don&#39;t plan to buy games exclusively this way, &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1061910&quot;&gt;Metal Hellsinger&lt;/a&gt; is my favourite game and it has DRM, but knowing that the vast majority of my game library is &lt;em&gt;mine&lt;/em&gt; while the fight between gamers and game studios rages on makes me feel warm inside. Buying through these storefronts gives gamers a way to show studios that this is what we want, hopefully paving the way for this to become the norm, not the exception.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 13:00:00 CDT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/how-to-own-your-pc-games/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trying Completely Degoogled Android: One Month Later</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/android-without-google-one-month/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello! This article is a followup on the previous article &amp;quot;Trying Completely Degoogled Android: Three Days Later&amp;quot;, where I took my Google Pixel 7 and installed a custom version of Android that had no dependency on Google whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d highly recommend going back and reading the &amp;quot;Three Days Later&amp;quot; article before this one; it highlights the process of setting up my Google Pixel 7 without Google Play Services, and some of the struggles that came with it. This is a smaller article to follow up on the original thoughts while I work on some larger articles in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Banking Apps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that my bank&#39;s mobile app works just fine without Google Play! After last time, where an e-transfer was detected as fraud by my bank, I logged into the app and it worked pretty much flawlessly. At the time, I thought it was because I had accidentally signed into the web portal on a VPN, but the employees told me it was more likely flagged because the amount I had transferred was very small (and could be less easily noticeable by a victim in that situation). Banking apps are one of more infamous categories of apps when trying to remove Google Play from a phone, but I happened to luck out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Battery Life and Push Notifications&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more noticeable things with using a degoogled phone was battery life. Most apps are reliant on Google Play Services to send push notifications to the user. Any exceptions to this rule, such as Signal, have to run their own push service. The problem is when every app has to run their own push service, it can have a noticeable (albeit not unusable) effect on battery life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more annoying is when apps that would benefit from their own push notification service don&#39;t have one implemented. By a landslide, the largest annoyance I have with my current workflow is Proton Mail. As of right now, I have to manually check the app for new emails, which is especially annoying considering that other Proton apps have perfectly functioning notifications, AND &lt;a href=&quot;https://k9mail.app/&quot;&gt;the other email app that I have on my phone&lt;/a&gt; for my school email has working notifications!! It&#39;s annoying enough that for anyone interested in the degoogling process who isn&#39;t already heavily invested into the Proton ecosystem, I&#39;d recommend a &lt;a href=&quot;https://tuta.com/&quot;&gt;Tuta email&lt;/a&gt;, where their app has their own push service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Web Browsers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing the &amp;quot;Three Days Later&amp;quot; article, I mentioned that I used Brave Browser. It still worked just as good as before deleting Google Play Services. Even though Brave is a great browser, I decided to move my main browser to something that isn&#39;t based off of Chromium. I chose Mull Browser, a privacy and security oriented fork of Firefox. Besides not supporting a couple PWA apps that I liked to use, it&#39;s been working just as well as Brave. I still use Brave on top of Mull for those PWA&#39;s that don&#39;t function properly, as well as for running into compatibility issues with Mull.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sometimes, Less is More&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I&#39;ve noticed about myself is that I spend a lot less time on my phone when Google Play Services aren&#39;t installed. My guess is that it&#39;s a combination of lesser access to the most popular games and social media apps, as well as generally being more aware about what I&#39;m installing on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;It&#39;s Working For Me!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I plan to stay with it in the long term! Everything that I need to work is still working, and there&#39;s a massive privacy benefit in having zero Google services running on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 13:00:00 CDT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/android-without-google-one-month/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trying Completely Degoogled Android: Three Days Later</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/android-without-google-3-days/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While I was doing research for switching to a more private phone, something that was really important to me was the ability to easily &amp;quot;Degoogle&amp;quot;, or remove any Google Services from the phone. Despite my choice of (ironically) a Google Pixel 7 for compatibility with GrapheneOS, I still had their sandboxed Google Play Services installed for a long time. As of March 25, 2024, I&#39;ve officially reset my phone, and chosen NOT to install Google Play Services again. Let&#39;s talked about what&#39;s worked great so far, as well as what&#39;s been problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grapheneos.org/&quot;&gt;GrapheneOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience with GrapheneOS so far is surprisingly phenomenal. Their main claim to fame is their sandboxed Google Play Services, which have to be installed by the user. It works exactly like regular Google Play Services, but it&#39;s treated like any other app, meaning the user can go in and restrict access to things like location or health data. It&#39;s an excellent feature, and extremely difficult to implement correctly, so props to the developers for the stability and ease of use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the entire point of this experiment is to move away from Google Play Services altogether. This meant I couldn&#39;t install Sandboxed Google Play Services, but GrapheneOS still works amazingly. They&#39;ve implemented security fixes that the stock Pixel devices haven&#39;t yet, and have a couple extra cool features like scrambled PIN codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d recommend anyone with a Pixel phone reading this to at least do some research and see if GrapheneOS with sandboxed Google Play Services is something that could work for them. &lt;a href=&quot;https://grapheneos.org/faq&quot;&gt;Their website has a great FAQ&lt;/a&gt; that answered a lot of the questions I had when I started out. Literally every app I used worked after some configuration, and it&#39;s pretty easy to get going thanks to their web-based installer. It&#39;s ironic that Google Pixel phones are the only supported devices at the moment, but it&#39;s still an excellent alternative to the stock operating system, and I plan to donate to help development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Messaging&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I expected messaging to be particularly difficult, and was pleasantly surprised. Despite using four different messaging apps, only one didn&#39;t maintain full functionality, which I&#39;ll talk about later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signal: This was one of the easiest apps to transition to a device without Google Play Services, but also one of the most complex under the hood because of Signal&#39;s minimal data collection. The good news was that the official client was designed to work this way, notifications and all. The bad news was that I had to create a backup of all my messages onto a flash drive in order to transfer it over. Thankfully, the backup worked pretty much flawlessly, and I&#39;ve been running the app exactly the same as I was before. This is another service alongside GrapheneOS that I plan to donate to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telegram: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Telegram-FOSS-Team/Telegram-FOSS&quot;&gt;Telegram FOSS&lt;/a&gt; is a fork of the official Telegram client, designed to remove all of the proprietary blobs of the official client. Using this client was vital, as notifications wouldn&#39;t work otherwise (I&#39;ll talk about this later). The nice part is that all the messages transferred over without a backup, something I couldn&#39;t say about any other app in this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatsapp: The messaging app that I use by far the least, which is a good thing because I couldn&#39;t find a way to perform a message backup without signing into a Google account. It&#39;s really annoying that I&#39;m locked into using it by only a couple important group chats, but at least it does still work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Open-Source Apps I was already using&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are applications that I just happened to be using that were already open source and designed to work without Google Play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/spacecowboy/Feeder&quot;&gt;Feeder&lt;/a&gt; - My RSS Feed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grayjay.app/&quot;&gt;Grayjay&lt;/a&gt; - a YouTube/Twitch/Nebula/etc client with solid privacy compared to the native clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tusky.app/&quot;&gt;Tusky&lt;/a&gt; - Mastodon client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://notesnook.com/&quot;&gt;Notesnook&lt;/a&gt; - Encrypted Note-taking app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Google Play Store apps that just work??&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, this was by far the most surprising thing to me. There&#39;s more than a few apps on the Google Play Store that work pretty much flawlessly without any problems on a degoogled phone, and GrapheneOS&#39;s protections make the apps more private than they would have been on a standard Google Pixel. I chose to install these apps without signing into a Google account through &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/whyorean/AuroraStore&quot;&gt;Aurora Store&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://plexus.techlore.tech/&quot;&gt;Plexus&lt;/a&gt; was a great start for researching what needed to be switched for an alternative, and what would just work anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;RCS Messaging&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the one messaging app with issues I eluded to earlier. Google&#39;s implementation of encrypted RCS messaging only works with Google Play Services installed. Hopefully, things will change with &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/16/apple-rcs-coming-to-iphone/&quot;&gt;Apple promising RCS support for iPhones in 2024&lt;/a&gt;. Until then, I&#39;m stuck with yucky SMS and MMS texting, ugh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worst case scenario, GrapheneOS has a messenger built-in, so I would be able to text in some form. I still wanted a nicer looking replacement, which is where &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/octoshrimpy/quik&quot;&gt;QUIK Messegner&lt;/a&gt; came in. Notifications are a minute or two late sometimes, but they do work. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tmo1/sms-ie?tab=readme-ov-file&quot;&gt;SMS Import/Export&lt;/a&gt; to transfer over messages and call logs from my previous phone, and it worked perfectly fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Notifications&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I eluded to earlier, a lot of apps rely on Google Play Services to deliver notifications properly. In fact, with Sandboxed Google Play Services on GrapheneOS, a toggle has to be enabled for unrestricted battery use in order for most notifications to arrive on time. This is why I had to use Telegram FOSS; All of the messaging apps have their own push notification service that run in the background to allow texts to arrive on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, not all of the apps I use have implemented a workaround. Proton Mail is the hardest pill to swallow; they&#39;ve been talking about implementing notifications without Google Play Services for awhile now, but have yet to actually do it. Any social media I use like Discord or Mastodon, as well as my browser also don&#39;t have working notifications without having the app open in the background. There&#39;s enough apps with working notifications that it&#39;s bearable, but it&#39;s still by far the most annoying aspect of degoogling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Banking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banking apps are infamously reliant on Google Play Services. In fact, lots of them must have the &amp;quot;Exploit Protection Compatibility Mode&amp;quot; enabled in GrapheneOS for them to function. I just assumed my banking app wouldn&#39;t work, and decided to switch to the website portal for what I needed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my biggest mistake so far, as I forgot about my VPN being connected. The bank locked my account because of a suspicious login from far away, even though it was my device. In one aspect, it&#39;s reassuring that they&#39;re watching that close to make sure my money doesn&#39;t get stolen. On the other hand, I still need to check the functionality of the native app, but if it doesn&#39;t work without Google Play Services, I don&#39;t have a great alternative for banking on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I plan to stick it out for now!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issues that I&#39;ve had so far, as big as they might be, are few and far between. Being able to work independently of Google Play Services with minimal changes to my workflow is really awesome for my digital privacy. With standard Google Play Services, especially on a Google Pixel phone, Google can track nearly everything about a user and tie it to their Google account. In my opinion, without all of that bloat and spyware, Android and GrapheneOS is better than IOS and the iPhone XR i upgraded from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone out there is looking to try this for themselves, my recommendation is to not do everything all at once. Start by looking into GrapheneOS with sandboxed Google Play Services, or by looking into what apps you can replace or delete that rely on Google Play Services. Progressive Web Apps are also very helpful, they won&#39;t require Google Play Services as long as the browser doesn&#39;t require it either. It took me almost a year to get to a point where I could comfortably delete Google Play Services entirely, and even then I&#39;m still running into a couple big problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to write about this again in a month or two, when I&#39;ve had more time to look into solutions for the problems I&#39;m having, or catch new problems that I haven&#39;t seen already.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 13:00:00 CDT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/android-without-google-3-days/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Defence of Telemetry</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/a-defence-of-telemetry/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Telemetry is a definitely a dirty word in the privacy sphere, and for good reason. The term is often associated with the disgustingly large amounts of data collected by Google, Meta, Microsoft, so on and so forth. Today, I write to argue in favour of telemetry... sometimes... when it&#39;s done right. There&#39;s a lot of conditions, but it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be done correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, obviously there&#39;s lots of privacy-invasive telemetry out there. I&#39;m not trying to claim that all telemetry is acceptable, or even that all privacy-oriented software has acceptable telemetry (Looking at you, Mozilla!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that being said, the problem with actively opposing telemetry for privacy reasons is the assumption that it is inherently privacy invasive. Now, that sounds contradictory. After all, how does a developer collect extra information without breaching privacy? Let&#39;s talk about some examples of services that I use daily, with telemetry enabled by my personal choice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Proton Suite&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, Proton Mail/Calendar/Drive/VPN/Pass, the Google suite replacement. One of the best known privacy services out there has telemetry enabled &lt;em&gt;by default&lt;/em&gt;. Creepy, right? Well, hold your horses for just a second, because it&#39;s a lot better under the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, while it isn&#39;t explicitly stated in the settings, they confirmed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/ProtonMail/comments/w21g41/deleted_by_user/&quot;&gt;in response to a Reddit post&lt;/a&gt; as well as their &lt;a href=&quot;https://proton.me/legal/privacy&quot;&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt; that all of the data they collect through these telemetry options is both completely anonymous, and never sold to any third parties. That&#39;s definitely a good start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what data do they collect in the first place? Well, the two toggles in the privacy settings are for &amp;quot;Usage Statistics&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Crash Reports&amp;quot;, both very reasonable things to collect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crash reports are obviously used to make the apps more stable, without this information the apps would have noticeably more problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usage statistics are a little bit tougher, but all we have to do is look at Firefox to understand. Most privacy-oriented modifications to Firefox, whether it be a fork or user.js profile, strip Mozilla&#39;s telemetry out of the program. Now consider how &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ugnOM2mzgNU&quot;&gt;lots of privacy enthusiasts are upset with direction Firefox has taken.&lt;/a&gt; Without feature usage statistics, Proton, as well as other application developers, are basically flying blind as to what their customers want.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proton is basically the perfect example of what I &lt;em&gt;expect&lt;/em&gt; from telemetry, the right balance between beneficial to the developers while still respecting user privacy. It&#39;s completely anonymous, very clear what they collect and what it&#39;s used for, and very easy to opt-out. Even though I pay the subscription for Proton Unlimited, I still have their telemetry enabled to further help the service improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;KDE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KDE is a Linux desktop environment that&#39;s very strongly recommended by privacy enthusiasts. Why does it have &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; telemetry at all? Well, the justification behind this is in the details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All telemetry is opt-in. Users have to actively search out the telemetry options and enable it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&#39;re very clear about the fact that they do not collect personal data, files, visited websites, or any identifying information at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They explicitly say that all telemetry is entirely anonymous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are multiple different levels of information that can be shared by the user, and they&#39;re very clear about what gets sent at every level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is about as far as I&#39;d expect any developer to go with privacy respecting analytics, without just flat out removing all telemetry. Being opt-in, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; very well hidden means that the vast majority of users won&#39;t enable it, especially with the main demographic being privacy enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Brave Browser&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brave has had it&#39;s fair share of controversies, but the way they handle telemetry is pretty good. Upon booting up the browser for the first time, users are given the option to disable all telemetry. It&#39;s opt-out, sure, but it&#39;s made very easy to find and disable, especially during the first boot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only telemetry that isn&#39;t explicitly labelled anonymous is crash reports, for stability improvements. Both their product analytics, and daily usage ping for estimating user count are entirely private. All three options are given separate toggles in the privacy settings, so a user can enable whichever options they&#39;d like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brave is also a perfect example of what happens to these sorts of products &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; any telemetry. One of the strongest elements of the Brave Browser is their randomised fingerprint protection; it&#39;s second to the Tor Browser, but without any of the speed penalties. However, a few months ago &lt;a href=&quot;https://brave.com/privacy-updates/28-sunsetting-strict-fingerprinting-mode/&quot;&gt;Brave decided to remove their stricter fingerprinting option that would break some websites&lt;/a&gt;. One of their main reasons for the decision was their analytics suggesting less than 0.5% of users enabled the feature. The thing is, most people enabling strict fingerprint protection are the same type of people to disable all telemetry. &lt;strong&gt;In this instance, disabling telemetry actively hurt the privacy options of users.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So what does acceptable telemetry look like?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This really depends on what your threat model looks like! Some people are digital ghosts, and want absolutely nothing tracked about them. For those use cases, I agree that telemetry of any amount is unwanted. My only concern with digital privacy is trying to be more aware of surveillance capitalism, and by extension unethical use of our personal data by big corporations. (Side note to myself; differing threat models would make for a really good post later on!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the traits that I look for before enabling telemetry of any kind on the programs I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&#39;s either opt-in, or very &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; easy to opt-out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The developer is very clear about what data is collected and why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All of the data collected is reasonable for improving their service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The telemetry is anonymous and cannot be tied back to my account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The developer doesn&#39;t sell the telemetry to any third parties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telemetry, when implemented ethically, is a good thing. We&#39;ve seen with Firefox, and especially Brave, how telemetry can affect the decisions that developers make with their products. As someone that&#39;s enthusiastic about some of these services being able to hit the mainstream, I like to enable telemetry to help the developers create a better product where I can, so that hopefully privacy can one day become the default rather than the niche.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 13:00:00 CDT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/a-defence-of-telemetry/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The World of Privacy-Respecting Smartwatches is Insane.</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/the-world-of-privacy-respecting-smartwatches-is-insane/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hoo boy. Smartwatches and privacy get along about as well as fire and oil. The main advantage over a traditional analog watch is in direct conflict with what privacy enthusiasts want; devices that are capable of tracking your sleep patterns, heart rate, stress levels, location, movement speed, and many other body traits are an absolute no-go. This isn&#39;t helped by the fact that most smartwatches upload data back to the servers of the company that maintains the product. Most people concerned that Google is tracking their browsing habits aren&#39;t exactly thrilled by the idea of that same company selling data about their sleeping habits to advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, these devices are some of the worst for digital privacy right alongside electric cars and IoT appliances. Around the summer of 2023, when I started taking my own digital privacy more seriously, I decided to switch from Apple to a privacy-focused Android operating system. Thankfully, I wasn&#39;t hard locked into Apple&#39;s ecosystem at the time, just an iPhone XR on it&#39;s last legs and... the Apple Watch. Rats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to research what options existed for a privacy-respecting smart watch. I wanted something that could communicate with my new Android phone, now that my Apple Watch was becoming a glorified paperweight. I also wanted something with the absolute bare minimum in health tracking, a heartbeat sensor. I thought these requirements were very simple, but I still didn&#39;t expect very many options to exist. In retrospect, maybe those requirements were a little... too simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buckle in. From fully functioning computers that fit around the wrist, to digital watches that have designs older than me, this is the comprehensive list of every option I considered when hunting for a privacy-respecting smartwatch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Casio F-91W&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, I know, okay? Just... listen. &lt;strong&gt;Hear me out.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it have communication with any external computer, never mind an Android phone? No, smartphones didn&#39;t really... well, didn&#39;t really exist when this first released in 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it have any tracking sensors whatsoever? Again, no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it even really qualify as a smartwatch? Probably not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for 20-30 Canadian dollars? It&#39;s &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard to complain. it&#39;s cheap enough to be an accessory to a regular smartwatch. It even carries some advantages over the several hundred dollar mini computers. Obviously price, but also longevity too! It has a coin battery that will last for years, if not decades. It&#39;s also a really tough nut to crack, capable of standing up many different extreme enviornments, and even being able to survive a good swim. It&#39;s actually not a terrible companion to what most people consider a proper smartwatch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here&#39;s where I pull the rug out: &lt;strong&gt;some mad scientist out there turned the thing into a smartwatch.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crowdsupply.com/oddly-specific-objects/sensor-watch&quot;&gt;Sensor Watch&lt;/a&gt; is a tiny hackable micro-controller that fits right inside the F91W shell, where the original electronics went. There&#39;s no wireless connectivity, and no modifications to the rest of the watch , meaning that any code that runs stays locally on the watch. No modifications also means it uses the original segmented screen of the F91W, so the battery still lasts upwards of a year. It can be turned into a digital thermometer, a sunrise/sunset timer based on latitude and longitude, and my personal favourite: a TOTP code generator! It&#39;s not very practical, especially relative to a few of the other options on this list, but for around 60 bucks combined for the base watch and the board it would make for a really fun project someday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PineTime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pine64&#39;s open source &lt;a href=&quot;https://pine64.com/product/pinetime-smartwatch-sealed/&quot;&gt;PineTime&lt;/a&gt; is the cheapest project on this list that I would actually consider as a daily driver smartwatch, not a niche item like the base F91W. Well, that isn&#39;t to say that the PineTime appeals to a wide demographic. with only 4.5MB of flash storage, and 64KB of RAM, the specs aren&#39;t going to blow anyone away. However, the more I researched, the more I realized just how impressive the PineTime truly was, especially considering the price tag...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I came to the conclusion that the value proposition here is outstanding, far better than I initially expected. For only a little more money than a base F91W, this is an actual smartwatch that offers all of the functionality I outlined: a heartbeat sensor, and connectivity with Android through the Bluetooth module. It even has a few extra goodies, like an accelerometer, week long battery, IPS touch display for good sunlight visibility, and even IP67 certification! I wouldn&#39;t go swimming with it, but it&#39;s still an impressive package for the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s most interesting about this device is the open-source aspect. From this point onward, I&#39;ll be referring to any device with both open source software and hardware (yes, there&#39;s multiple) as &amp;quot;hackwatches&amp;quot;. The creators of these hackwatches usually provide documentation of how the watch works, meaning that those who have the technical know-how could create their own programs. That level of flexibility (again, assuming the user has the coding knowledge) is something unheard of on more mainstream options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pine64 definitely created a F91W + Sensor Watch killer, although most people are more likely interested in these low-level hackable projects as a novelty, and not an actual daily driver smartwatch. I&#39;d go as far to say that PineTime offers the best value proposition of any watch on this list, just don&#39;t expect the same functionality as an Apple Watch or similarly priced products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Watchy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of any hackwatches on this list, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crowdsupply.com/sqfmi/watchy&quot;&gt;Watchy&lt;/a&gt; is by far the most unique. The E-Ink display provides several advantages over a traditional LCD screen. E-Ink displays are easier on the eyes (no blue light!), provide better sunlight visibility, and better battery life (the screen uses no power if the display is static). It has full accelerometer, WiFi, and Bluetooth functionality, which is pretty impressive at the price tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any of the other hackwatches on this list, the device is fully programmable by the end user. This also has the advantage of the most buttons out of any watch on the list, a total of four. That many buttons might actually open some opportunities for custom programs that wouldn&#39;t be possible on watches with only one or two buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is definitely a better value for the money than the F91W + Sensor Watch, but things become a little murkier when comparing to the PineTime. Watchy is about twice the price of the PineTime, albeit still very cheap. Watchy has 8 times the ram (64KB -&amp;gt; 520KB), replaces the heartbeat sensor for a WiFi module, and lacks some smartwatch-esque features (touchscreen, water and dust resistance). Watchy (agh, such a fun name) makes sense as a basic wearable computer, while PineTime makes sense as an extremely basic programming smartwatch. Which one I would recommend over the other depends on what features the user would rather experiment with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bangle.js&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s where things start to get interesting. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.espruino.com/Bangle.js2&quot;&gt;Bangle.js 2&lt;/a&gt; is a bridge between these open source hackwatches, and more feature rich smartwatches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Costing around 130 in Canadian money, this is by far the most expensive hackwatch on the list. Accordingly, it also has the most sensors and features. Bluetooth connectivity, an accelerometer, IP67 rating, and a heart rate sensor are all included. Unique to the hackwatch space, Bangle.js includes a magnetometer, air pressure/temperature sensor, and GPS functionality. That last point is especially important, as proprietary smartwatches with GPS functionality tend to err on the pricier side. The next cheapest smartwatch I could find with GPS functionality was about 70 loonies more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Small teaser; the brand that sold that smartwatch also happened to be the same brand I chose in the end!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;AsteroidOS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asteroidos.org/&quot;&gt;AsteroidOS&lt;/a&gt; is an alternate Linux operating system designed to operate on smartwatches developed by larger companies. It explicitly has the goal of providing users better privacy and control over their data. An on-device app store doesn&#39;t exist, but programs can be installed manually when connected to a desktop. Something worth noting is that AsteroidOS has absolutely zero compatibility with WearOS, Google&#39;s Android-based operating system that&#39;s found on most mainstream smartwatches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AsteroidOS supports a very specific list of smartwatches, with varying degrees of functionality. All of the smartwatches with official support are proprietary hardware, which means I don&#39;t consider devices with AsteroidOS a hackwatch. What really turned me off from AsteroidOS was the price of adoption. Most compatible smartwatches were relatively old and would need to be purchased second-hand. Not only that, but when searching for compatible watches on eBay and my areas second-hand market, most were price equal, or even more expensive than new smartwatches, including the watch that I eventually settled on. Especially with the right deal, this doesn&#39;t seem like a terrible option, just not for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apple Watch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my choice of smartwatch before I started considering digital privacy more seriously, and it actually wasn&#39;t a terrible choice. Generally speaking, Apple&#39;s privacy policy is a step above Google&#39;s privacy policy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/privacynotincluded/apple-watch/&quot;&gt;According to Mozilla&#39;s Privacy Not Included article&lt;/a&gt;, user health data is encrypted, both on device and in iCloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if the Apple Watch was the perfect solution, I would still have to find an alternative. During the summer of 2023, I purchased an Android phone second hand to replace my iPhone XR and installed a privacy-oriented OS on it. Unfortunately, this left me without a device to properly control the Apple Watch. If you&#39;re already using an iPhone, the Apple Watch is unparalleled in functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And the Winner Is...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research eventually led me to a smartwatch company that genuinely seems to be trying their best to create a privacy-respecting smartwatch experience: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garmin.com/en-CA/&quot;&gt;Garmin.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Endorsed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/privacynotincluded/?search=Garmin#product-review&quot;&gt;Mozilla&#39;s Privacy Not Included&lt;/a&gt;, Garmin has one of the best privacy policies... well, in general, never mind just smartwatch companies. They have a very clear, readable privacy policy that states don&#39;t sell your data, and give you the option to delete your data at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Garmin&#39;s software is also very impressive from a privacy perspective. If, for whatever reason, a customer is still concerned about their data after reading the privacy policy, watches and fitness trackers from this brand maintain most of their functionality without being connected to a phone through Bluetooth or via the internet. Data can be extracted from the watch to a computer via a wired cable, and ran through open source software for analysis. They run a customized operating system independent of WearOS, so data won&#39;t be relayed through Google during usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pricing is also very competitive. Remember the cheapest GPS-enabled smartwatch alluded to earlier? That title belongs to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garmin.com/en-CA/p/714945&quot;&gt;Garmin Bounce&lt;/a&gt; at 200 Canadian pesos. My personal choice was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garmin.com/en-CA/p/742133/pn/010-02566-00&quot;&gt;Garmin Vivomove Sport&lt;/a&gt;, a stylish hybrid analog/digital watch with functionality between between the Bangle.js 2 hackwatch, and the (much more expensive) Apple Watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Garmin smartwatches are the product that I would reccomend for most people. For technically skilled folks, Bangle.js 2 offers most of the functionality of Garmin at a cheaper price, while staying more private. For any digital ghosts out there, the F91W with the Sensor Watch upgrade actually makes the most sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being completely unexpected, I was delighted at how many different options existed for privacy enthusiasts! Everyone, from those very casually interested in privacy, to digital ghosts that live in the woods, have options! Even though i settled with Garmin, I&#39;m still interested in a hackwatch as a programming project, and AsteroidOS would also be interesting to look at in the future. It&#39;s really fun to see so much competiton in a field that seems pretty stiff in terms of competition at first, especially in the niche of privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 12:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/the-world-of-privacy-respecting-smartwatches-is-insane/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Signal is Important, and How to Get Contacts on Signal</title>
      <link>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/how-to-get-contacts-on-signal/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the largest problems with trying to become digitally private in our world is a lack of mass adoption of privacy-respecting software. YouTube, Twitter/X, Discord, Microsoft Office, and so on all have privacy respecting alternatives out there. However, the user base of these programs is tiny relative to the big corporations offerings, meaning a worse experience in several ways. Every so often, a privacy-oriented app garners mainstream attention. As a privacy enthusiast, it&#39;s important to me to endorse these programs when they make a splash, as they&#39;re the best chance at changing the status quo for digital privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With over 40 million users as of the start of 2022, Signal is one of very few success stories in the privacy world that has seen adoption by the general public. They developed the Signal Protocol, an encryption standard used by WhatsApp, Google&#39;s RCS implementation, and others. Their own encrypted messenger is just about as convenient to setup and use as its competitors, such as WhatsApp or Telegram. Unlike those competitors, Signal doesn&#39;t know anything about their users contact info, their contacts list, location data, or anything about their users besides when they signed up, and the last day they accessed the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Signal&#39;s relative success in mainstream adoption, it&#39;s still far from the default option. WhatsApp, Telegram, and iMessage are usually the default for most. However, it&#39;s still possible to convince friends and family to switch to a platform that&#39;s truly private. I&#39;ve personally been able to convince around 20 people to switch to Signal very passively, only actually asking people to switch once at most. Here&#39;s how I did it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don&#39;t be a Jerk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People won&#39;t want to download this new app for you if you&#39;re rude to them about why they should switch. When talking to people about switching, be polite and don&#39;t be upset with them if they say no. Simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Know Your Audience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asking someone to switch to Signal, consider the kind of person you&#39;re talking to and what might be of interest to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are they already signed up for Signal? Perfect, just ask to move your conversations to that platform!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are they digitally literate or technologically skilled? Cool, they might better understand the privacy and security benefits of switching to Signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How are you in contact with them in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SMS/MMS: Firstly, ew. Also, Signal is so much better in nearly every conceivable way, just asking nicely might get you there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other Messengers without encryption: While some of these have better features than Signal, Almost anyone could potentially read them, including the company providing the service. For important personal conversations, Signal is the better option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Messages &amp;amp; RCS: Better than SMS/MMS, but Signal still wins. From a security perspective, group chats are not encrypted through Google&#39;s implementation of RCS. From a feature perspective, SIgnal also offers some extra features over Google Messages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WhatsApp/iMessage/Other Encrypted Messengers: Depending on the person you&#39;re talking to, you might be able to explain the concept of metadata and how Signal collects the absolute bare minimum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else might they be convinced by? These are some of the more obvious traits and how to approach them, but it&#39;s really a case-by-case basis. Maybe they&#39;d be convinced by a celebrity endorsement, or by the freedom of speech argument, or by something else! It&#39;s really up to you to decide what each of your contact&#39;s priorities are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prepare for Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be helpful to be prepared for questions that people might have about the service. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/kt91qk/signal_private_messenger_team_here_we_support_an/&quot;&gt;Here&#39;s a link to a Reddit AMA that Signal did a few years back&lt;/a&gt;, which might be indicative about some of the questions people have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important to note is that &lt;a href=&quot;https://signal.org/blog/phone-number-privacy-usernames/&quot;&gt;as of February 20, Signal has announced the addition of usernames coming over the next few weeks.&lt;/a&gt; While users still need a phone number to sign up, nobody, including Signal themselves, has to have access to it. Phone numbers are only required to prevent the creation of spam accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Move Away From Other Services the Best You Can&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make Signal the easiest place to get in contact with you. I still have both WhatsApp and Telegram for people that refuse to switch, but my profile picture on both platforms is set to this image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/pinkish/signal_switch.webp&quot; alt=&quot;signal_switch&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has actually helped convince some friends to switch over. The people that want to keep in contact with you, and the people you should want to stay in contact with, will be willing to sacrifice a few megabytes of storage this way. Whether you want to completely delete these accounts or not is up to you. Personally, I&#39;m not comfortable going that nuclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Not Everyone Will be Willing to Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s okay! I have yet to see someone, online or in-person, convince literally every contact of theirs to switch to Signal. Being able to convince most, or even just a few of your contacts to switch to Signal, has benefits. For one, it still &lt;em&gt;minimizes&lt;/em&gt; the messages that are vulnerable to spying by third parties &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2023/11/9/23953798/automakers-collect-record-text-messages-federal-judge-ruling&quot;&gt;like car manufacturers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, more societal benefit is demonstrating the demand for digital privacy. Just recently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/16/apple-rcs-coming-to-iphone/&quot;&gt;Apple announced not only that they plan to adopt RCS this year, but that they want to work with the GSMA to add encryption to the RCS standard.&lt;/a&gt; This will be a massive improvement over SMS and MMS, which are about as old as the Super NES and have no encryption whatsoever. If the increased security and encryption ends up working out as well, That would be an improvement over Google&#39;s implementation of RCS, which currently doesn&#39;t encrypt group chats. Signal Messenger and Signal Protocol were likely large contributors to showing Apple that there was a demand for better, encrypted messaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signal is undeniable proof that privacy-by-default is a realistic goal. Showing big tech companies that there&#39;s consumer demand for ethical management of user data is an important step in motivating them to do so. In order to show the demand, users need to switch to platforms and services that respect their privacy more, and Signal is the golden standard to prove the viability of that concept.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 12:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Dex</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://dextersig.ca/blog/posts/how-to-get-contacts-on-signal/</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>